Hello, welcome everyone. It is August
6th, 2025. We're live in Octream
number 116.1
with returning guest Max Apher who will
be discussing this paper solving the
compute crisis with physicsbased basics.
Max will go over the paper, talk about a
few different things, then I will check
in the live chat and read any questions
that people have. So, looking forward to
people's questions, and Max, thank you
again for joining. Looking forward to
the presentation.
>> All right. Um, thank you for the
introduction. Yes, I'm Max Cipher and I
work with Normal Computing. Um, and and
um, as Daniel mentioned, this is my
second time uh, on the stream with the
Active Inference Institute. the the
first time I was talking about a paper
called uh thermodynamic basian inference
um which an example of one of our
algorithms we've been developing in in
thermodynamic computing and this time
I'm going to be talking about this this
new perspective article uh we we've
written called uh solving the compute
crisis with physics-based AS6 um and
just a little word about the background
on this uh this kind of emerged out of a
um an industry like workshop that uh
normal computing the company I work at
we hosted did at our our office in New
York uh because we had been focusing up
to that point on uh and still are on on
the ideas of thermodynamic computing and
applying those to machine learning and
in particular you know probabistic
machine learning. Um but we noticed that
there's a lot of other uh people both in
industry and and academia working on um
different approaches to unconventional
computing and we figured well there must
be something that uh we can learn from
each other. So we hosted this workshop
and it turned out um I think that a kind
of more a larger like unifying framework
uh started to emerge that there's a
bigger picture of of something that
these different approaches have in
common. Even though even though when we
move beyond uh the standard digital
paradigm we're familiar with we get kind
of a zoo of strange exotic new uh
components and circuits that we're
using. there is still some kind of
pattern or structure uh that we can
identify and categorize to think about
these things. Uh and so that was kind of
where this uh paper came out of that um
us and the other people who were at that
workshop thought it was worth writing a
paper on. Um and so I'm going to uh
after I kind of finish you know giving a
little bit of the background and
overview I'll kind of scroll through the
paper and uh give more detailed and
explanations and commentary on it. And
also of course I encourage you know
anyone to uh go and check it out for
yourself. Uh so this is a perspective
article and there we're not going to be
pres presenting new like um theoretical
results in here per se or simulation
results but it's more of our view of of
um the connections between these
different uh computing paradigms and
where we see the the field going. Um but
in a nutshell, I guess it's um the
reason why I think we see so many of
these new exotic computing paradigms uh
starting to take off now is because
there's kind of a a new challenge uh for
computing uh which is the amount of
compute that's required for AI is just a
very large amount of compute and it
requires a very large amount of energy.
Um and that's not you know not I guess a
new challenge for computing in a way and
that there have always been new
algorithms that demanded more compute
but there is something different about
it uh which I'll get into when I talk
about the end of dinard scaling in that
we'll have to solve it in a different
way than it was solved before um and so
I guess that the at a high level you can
kind of think of it as instead of just
trying to make uh chips bigger or cram
more transistors onto a chip um people
are now looking into ways of uh using a
different kind of fundamental structure
for computing or replacing uh you know
using something else instead of a
transistor to do computing logic gates
uh or storing information um or taking
those uh transistors we have and using
them in a different way um modeling
their behavior in a more complicated way
uh and and um and of course there's also
ways we can rethink the architecture of
of a chip something like a GPU or CPU
there are a lot of kind of things in
common in the in the circuit
architecture from one to another and
that hasn't been haven't been changed
very much in a long time at least in you
know big commercial platforms and so
people are also thinking of new kind of
novel architectures uh and the um the
kind of family of approaches I'm going
to be talking about are what we call
physics-based AS6 which we've kind of
introduced this term and and given a bit
of a definition in this paper um but
What you can think of it as is is saying
instead of trying to abstract the
physics away and treating my circuit as
something that behaves like an ideal
model of computation like a touring
machine or finite state machine, I'm
going to actually model the physics of
the uh components of a circuit and use
those in an algorithm somehow. So I'm
going to use uh you know physical
components on my chip and pay attention
to what kind of physical processes they
undergo and trying to exploit those uh
to do some kind of useful computation.
Um so uh and and then of course we can
get into like the idea of uh hardware
algorithm codees where we kind of look
at two different things. We look at like
what are the kinds of physical processes
that uh this device can do and then on
the other hand we look at what kinds of
processes are useful for my algorithm or
what what kind of primitive operations
are needed by the algorithm I'm trying
to run and we try to kind of find the
overlap uh between those two uh like
categories basically and that's uh
basically what a lot of us are working
on um more or less right now including
at at uh normal computing is this
approach to hardware algorithm code
design. Um so that's kind of the highle
overview I guess of the ideas in the
paper and so now I guess I'll I'll go
into a little bit more detail. Um so um
I had mentioned earlier that the problem
of having applications algorithms that
require a lot of compute uh is not a new
problem per se. Um but the thing that is
different is that we are now kind of
firmly in the like post Dinard scaling
era and uh arguably in the post Moors
law era. Uh so I guess I'll I'll say a
little bit about what that means. Um so
what dinard scaling was about was that
um for a long time you know decades up
until the early 2000s uh when people
made new uh microprocessors made new
CPUs and and I guess GPUs towards the
end of that time period um they would
shrink the transistors you know they
make the transistors smaller so they
could fit more transistors on a chip
right and this is how uh how Mo's law
which is maybe a little bit more um more
people are a little bit are familiar
with more law than did scaling. Uh but
both were driven by that uh trend that
people would make transistors smaller
and so they could fit more transistors
on a chip of the same size. Um but what
uh Dinard noticed is that when you make
a transistor smaller that also changes
uh the amount of power that you need to
operate it because the supply voltage is
also reduced by the same factor when you
make that transistor smaller. Um, so
this was really great, right? Uh, you
know, in engineering, it's not so often
that you get something that's like a
kind of a free lunch, but this was maybe
the closest thing you could get for a
free to a free lunch is that we we make
the transistors smaller and not only can
we have more on the chip, but they
consume less power, they're also going
to dissipate less heat, so that helps us
out with with cooling, right? Um and uh
one way of kind of summarizing that uh
that idea is that um independent of how
small your transistors are in the in the
diner in the dinard scaling era the um
density of power consumed per unit area
was constant. Uh so in other words, if I
have a chip that's you know a centimeter
by a centimeter, doesn't matter how many
transistors are on it, a million, a
billion or a trillion or whatever, we
would assume that they would all consume
the same amount of power. Um and so that
was in a nutshell like how the
challenges of more and more demanding
applications was met historically was
that we would make the transistor
smaller, put more on the chip uh and we
would also have better energy efficiency
because of dinard scaling. But the
reason that will so I guess yeah dinard
scaling ended in like around you know
people will say different years maybe
2005 something around there maybe a
little earlier. Um but the reason it
ended is is that there are actually not
every um not every electrical electrical
property of the transistor scales in the
same way when you make it smaller. And
in particular, it was uh without going,
you know, too deep into detail here, it
it ended up being turning out that the
leakage current and the threshold
voltage don't scale in that way. Um and
so we could only kind of make them so
small uh and keep reducing the power
consumption. And then so once
transistors were small enough that the
leakage current became, you know, very
important that that uh trend ended. And
so after that um you know we could still
make transistors smaller to some extent
but that wouldn't really uh change the
power. They would still consume you know
roughly the same amount of power. And so
that started to create problems for
cooling right because we can cram more
and more transistors in a small area but
that means the power the density of
power per unit area is now going to
start increasing uh after the end of
dinard scaling. Uh and so people would
do things like say we're only going to
turn on part of the chip at a time
because otherwise there would just be
too much heat, stuff like that. Um and
that was really what uh I think kicked
off kind of like the multicore era where
where people then started to say, well,
because we can't really get much more
mileage by just making the transistor
smaller and putting more on the on the
chip, what we're going to start doing is
well, we're going to have multiple
processors basically. Uh and so when we
need more compute, we'll just get more
processors, we'll get more chips, and
then we'll try to parallelize our
algorithms. Um we'll try to make our
algorithms into we'll try to solve our
problem using an algorithm that can
efficiently effectively be parallelized
across multiple chips that with a
minimal amount of communication between
them. Uh and that basically brings us to
where we are today where you know the
GPU general purpose GPU is is the
dominant paradigm for um you know some
of the most important algorithms
particularly in um AI now. Um so yeah I
guess that's kind of the the starting
point and then the question is well what
are you know what are the problems with
this GPU paradigm or is is this um is
this way of scaling things up just
getting more and more GPUs uh going to
um going to work or if not you know why
are we considering these physics based
AS6 instead uh well so basically the the
issue is that right now um the because
of this uh situation where we can't um
reduce power consumption just by making
the transistor smaller. If you have, you
know, twice as many GPUs, they're going
to be consuming twice the amount of
power. And so there's, you know, a huge
increase in the amount of energy that's
consumed due to like AI that's
anticipated with people putting power
plants in their data centers or or data
centers in their power plants or however
you want to look at it. um just because
you need a huge amount of energy to to
power you know training um particularly
training maybe even inference to some
extent as now um and then also there's
just the sheer cost of getting all that
hardware right the um the cost of buying
all the GPUs that you need to do a
training run for a you know foundation
model um and so that's why you have the
you know the the big uh companies like
OpenAI and etc saying that they're
literally you know melting their GPU are
melting because uh there's just too much
um throughput basically uh for for them
to handle. Um so that's why we're
they're that's basically the summary of
the problem that we're trying to solve
uh or that we're we're talking about
different solutions to that problem in
this uh perspective article. Um
okay so I think that's also a good point
to transition into talking about uh the
idea of hardware algorithm uh code
design. Um so I mentioned that because
uh the way that we're scaling up compute
now is getting more chips and we need to
parallelize our algorithms. Um the
dominant algorithms that we see in the
model architectures that we see in AI
are ones that can be parallelized very
effectively. Um and that's something
that was pointed out in a a well you
know a well-known paper called the
hardware lottery. Um and it was talking
about how model architectures like
transformers uh and and so on which are
powering you know the large language
models are not necessarily better than
many other approaches different
approaches from a first principles like
algorithmic standpoint. But the reason
why they're so successful and these
algorithms have have kind of won out is
because they they um are more suitable
for the hardware paradigm. uh they
parallelize better on GPUs. Uh and so
that's something that in many now have
kind of come around to that view that
the the transformer the reason why it's
so successful and uh prevalent I guess
is is not because it's better than you
know other solutions uh like recurrent
neural networks or or LSTM or whatever
but just because it parallelizes better
on GPUs. Um now we can kind of take this
line of thinking and uh generalize it a
little bit further in that um so clearly
uh it's not just the a question of like
how good is the hardware or how good is
the algorithm but the question of how
suitable is the are the algorithms and
hardware for each other is kind of
equally important. Um so that's kind of
maybe a slightly more general way of
thinking about that idea of the hardware
lottery. And um if we think about you
know how does it make sense for us to um
design better algorithms and hardware uh
from that perspective um I think there's
a good case to be made that we don't
want to treat it as two separate
optimization problems of either on the
one hand we'll consider the algorithm
fixed and we'll try to make the hardware
uh as fast as possible for running that
algorithm or on the other hand we'll
consider the hardware fixed and we'll
design the algorithm to run as fast as
possible on that hardware. But instead
of either of those, we approach it as a
joint optimization problem as how do we
design the bo best combination of a
hardware and an algorithm to solve this
problem uh you know as efficiently as
possible. And so that approach is
hardware algorithm codees. Uh and and
many of you know the ideas in this paper
physics based AS6 are taking a code
approach uh like that I guess. Um
so I guess at that with that said I'll
start to jump into like what uh what is
a physics-based ASIC um and and how do
we even uh define that? Um
so I'll start out with kind of an
observation about why we think that um
using the physics of devices can give us
more uh you know more computational
power basically. Uh so we give an
example in the perspective article of
the problem of simulating the behavior
of a single transistor right so uh you
could think of it as well if if I have
you know a software like spice or
cadence or something they have some
models behavior models of how a
transistor behaves uh or like you know
given the input signals what are the
output signals and so on. Um,
but to have like a really detailed
physical model of a transistor uh that
that kind of totally explains all of its
observable behavior, you would need to
uh well well one way you could do it is
you could solve a system of of partial
differential partial differential
equations uh for for the transistor um
with you know many variables, many
degrees of freedom. Uh, and if you
wanted to like run that simulation on a
on a standard like digital computer, you
would end up using, you know, billions
of transistors at least or or more to
simulate this one transistor. Uh, you'd
be and you'd be doing, you know, a huge
number of of flops, you know,
floatingoint operations just for a
single time step to sim simulate that
one transistor. Um and so once we kind
of realize that uh we can say well if it
turned out that the behavior of a single
transistor kind of the detailed physical
behavior was actually useful um
for some application then instead of
running this very costly simulation we
could just use that single transistor um
as kind of its own we uh its own its own
model of its own behavior basically
instead of you know some simulation of
it basically Um so that's like kind of
the intuition for why we think that like
hidden in the physics of common like uh
computa common like circuit components.
There's a lot of computation in there
that's that's hidden in there somewhere.
But then the question is well is that
computation useful? So then we need to
say well what are the um primitive
operations that are useful for the
algorithms that we want to run and is
there some way for us to map them on to
the physics of you know circuit uh
components. Okay. Okay. So, now that
I've got kind of covered that intuition,
I'll start to walk through um more of a
more of a definition, I guess, or maybe
as close as we come to a definition in
in the perspective article for physics
based AS6. Um and the way we think we're
thinking about it is that um so first of
all, all integrated circuits use physics
to do computing. um there's no you know
there's no such thing as a as a circuit
that doesn't uh use physics because that
ultimately the the physics of the
circuit and Kirchoff's laws and etc are
going to govern the behavior. So what do
we really mean when we say a circuit
that is using physics to compute? Well,
for one thing, in in any kind of common
like run-of-the-mill integrated circuit
uh that you'll find, there are a lot of
um well, they they uh basically kind of
abstract away from the physics so that
it's possible to treat the circuit as an
idealized model of computation like a
finite state machine or a touring
machine or something like that. And in
order to make that possible so that you
can kind of ignore the physics and
design algorithms on a higher level of
abstraction, uh we need to suppress a
lot of kind of messy behaviors that you
would see that you would find in systems
in in nature uh and in you know kind of
generic you know dynamical systems in
physics. But you don't really observe
these behaviors in uh circuits that
we've designed. And so here are some
examples of those those messy behaviors
that we try to uh design integrated
circuits to suppress. So one is like uh
statefulness. Um so in a um in an
integrated circuit there's a clear
separation between memory and compute.
uh you know you have some transistors
that and and capacitors etc that are
responsible for storing bits of
information for storing data and other
ones that are in logic gates that are uh
responsible for processing that data um
and and now more recently people are
kind of starting to merge the two uh and
that's I think kind of starts to fall
within the realm of physics-based AS6
but in the conventional paradigm you
have this clear separation between um
you know logical operations and memory
Um and what that means is that the the
circuits that are responsible for the um
logical operations are supposed to
behave statelessly. Uh and so as an
example of that, let's say that I have
like a not gate uh and I input a zero,
it outputs a one. I input a one, it
outputs a zero. Um it's only its output
is only supposed to depend on the input
it's getting at any given time. is not
supposed to its output isn't supposed to
depend on previous inputs that it's
gotten or in other words it's not
supposed to be kind of maintaining some
internal state that keep that that uh
keeps track of its history basically
it's supposed to behave statelessly. So
that's one way in which uh circuits are
designed to suppress kind of a common
like generic physical behavior because
most dynamical systems in in nature of
course are stateful and the way that
they behave will depend on on their
history. Uh so that's one example.
Another one is um unidirectionality of
of the flow of information. Uh so I'll
take the example of a notgate again. Um
if I change the voltage at the input,
the voltage at the output is supposed to
change in response to that. Uh but we're
not supposed to have information going
back the other way. It it shouldn't uh
if I applied a voltage change the
voltage at the output, that shouldn't uh
affect the the voltage at the input. Um
and and that's designing logicates and
uh you know components that satisfy this
kind of unidirectionality
makes the like engineering of circuits a
lot easier because you can treat uh
logic gates as blocks in a feed forward
network where information propagates
through one block and then through the
next one and you don't have to worry
about like kind of unwanted feedback
loops where information you know just
kind of spontaneously goes propagates
back through to the beginning of the
circuit. Um and of course you can design
circuits uh with feedback loops and and
many circuits do have feedback loops
like the one illustrated here. But the
the point being though the the feedback
loop has to be built in explicitly. So
here you have a you know logicates
processing bits uh a memory device a
flop is updated and then a signal is is
taken back to the beginning by some some
wire. And this is the way that you know
feedback loops are created in digital
circuits because you're not supposed to
have information shouldn't flow back
through the same logic gate. Uh okay. So
and then again if you compare this to
how like um physical systems in nature
behave they often don't have like
unidirectional flow of information. They
have birectional flow of information. So
you think of for example Newton's law
you know for every action there's an
equal and opposite reaction. If you or
if you have two masses on a spring, if
mass A is connected to mass B, if if B
is pulled in one direction by A, then A
is, you know, pulled in the other
direction by B. And analogously, if we
think of like an analog circuit where
you have different capacitors coupled to
each other in some, you know, resistive
network or something, uh they'll both,
you know, be sharing charge with with
each other and and will their voltages
will will both be changing at the same
time with information flowing in both
directions. Uh so, okay. Okay. So,
unidirectionality was another example of
how conventional AS6 suppress a kind of
a generic physical behavior um to to
make uh them conform to some like ideal
model of computation. Another important
one is determinism. So, a circuit is uh
given if you give the same input
multiple times, it should give the same
output each time. And of course you can
use uh you know a deterministic circuit
for randomized algorithms if you want.
Um and that'll generally be done using a
pseudo random number generator which is
you know still going to be implemented
by the determin a deterministic
algorithm on a deterministic circuit. Um
but the point being the circuit itself
is supposed to uh you know to a very
good approximation behave in a
deterministic way where you give it the
same input in the same you get the same
output. Uh and so that's another you
know thing that is not um well it's not
per it's not possible to realize that
perfectly uh it's only possible to
realize it to a good approximation
because of course all systems in nature
have fluctuations they have noise uh
which is guaranteed by uh
thermodynamics. Um, and so in order to
uh suppress those fluctuations or at
least make them um or protect against
them so that you don't have random bit
flips all the time, that's always going
to cost some amount of energy uh and
there's going to need need to be some
kind of safeguards or error correction
or whatever built in uh to enable this
uh idealized deterministic behavior. Uh
so that was a third example of a kind of
a behavior that um we is suppressed in
in conventional AS6. And then I think
the the last uh example we gave here was
um synchronization. So when we have you
know some very large circuit uh on a
chip that with many different you know
many different parts all doing something
at the same time there is typically
going to be like a global clock that is
sending out a clock pulse signal to you
know all different parts of the chip at
the same time. Um and so all parts of
the chip are synchronized with with each
other and with the centralized clock. Um
now this is another kind of behavior
that we don't often see in um in systems
we find in nature. There are many
systems that exhibit synchronization to
some extent but often synchronization
happens in a distributed way. uh so you
know or if you have um something like a
kuramoto model for example which uh can
be used to model how um I I believe it's
used to model how neurons synchronize
with each other in the brain or or
things like that often models of
synchronization that are supposed to be
realistic or ones that are supposed to
model how synchronization actually
happens in nature are using a a kind of
distributed model of synchronization
where different um different kind of
components will talk to each other, but
they're not all talking to one
centralized clock. And of course, there
are exceptions to that. Uh, but that's
probably the more like generic physical
situation where you have uh if you have
synchronization, it happens in a
distributed way and then often in
arbitrary dynamical systems, you won't
really have any synchronization at all.
Um so this was another behavior that
where we're kind of building in
something uh where we we're going
through some effort to give our system a
property that is kind of uncommon to
find in nature is somewhat un unnatural
somehow. And so for all of these
properties that allow us to treat
integrated circuits as idealized models
of computation, we're going to pay some
cost in order to make them to realize
these properties approximately. uh and
and they can generally they can only be
realized approximately not perfectly. Uh
and in general we're going to incur some
additional costs in terms of dissipation
uh you know how much yeah how much
energy is dissipated um and in terms of
speed. So uh in order to make these
approximately true we're going to have
to accept some limitation on how fast we
can run our circuit. Uh a good example
probably being like synchronization. If
you imagine that every part of the chip
needs to be synchronized to that global
clock pulse, well, it takes some amount
of time for that clock pulse to reach
all the different parts of the chip. So
that could be a limitation on how fast
you can make your clock cycles, right?
Because you need to allow enough time uh
for the the clock pulse to reach all the
different parts of the chip. Um
similarly determinism is going to incur
some cost because we need to suppress
noise or or make our signals large
enough that the noise is like neg
negligible relative to the signals which
is a common uh way of of making circuits
deterministic. Um and so this
observation that these idealized
properties all incur some cost in terms
of energy or time or something like
that. uh generally energy and time. Uh
because of that we started to say well
what if we design circuits without
worrying about these properties or
saying we're going to relax these
requirements that they they have these
properties and then maybe our circuits
will be more energy efficient and maybe
they'll run faster. uh but then we'll
have to kind of think in a more
complicated way when we design our
algorithms because we can no longer or
when even when we design our circuit
both the circuits and the algorithms
because it's not as easy to uh for
example to compose operations uh because
now instead of treating each component
as a a block you know element that uh
feeds information for that you know has
unidirectional information flow and is
stateless and deterministic. Now we each
component is kind of a little bit more
messy and we have these messy behaviors
that we need to uh you know deal with
somehow when we design our algorithms.
Um so that's kind of I guess how I would
think about like defining um what a
physics based ASIC is is an ASIC that is
designed uh which is not designed to
satisfy all of these properties
approximately um and uh violates you
know at least one of them or and often
times more uh and as a result we hope to
be able to um make circuits more energy
efficient uh you know and faster that
way. Um so now I've kind of given you
know a model for like how to think about
what a physics based as um I guess I can
talk a little bit about like some
examples to uh approaches here. Um but
actually I guess before I go into the
examples of hardware paradigms maybe
I'll pause and see if there were any um
any questions that came up in in the
chat and and if there were I can I can
take some of those. Um, I'll just read
two helpful comments by your colleague
Patrick Kohl's who wrote, "Join
optimization, optimizing the hardware
and algorithms together can be more
powerful
than individually optimizing them
independently. And in a sense, the more
properties on this list that you assume,
the more you move away from physics,
what physics does naturally." Sorry
about the audio, by the way.
>> Oh, no worries. Great. Yeah, I thought
those were great comments. Thanks.
Thanks for the comments, Patrick. Okay.
Um All right, great. Well, so I guess
I'll I'll keep uh you know, pressing
forward and and talk about a few
examples of like kind of hardware
paradigms that start to um abandon some
of these properties I guess in in
various ways. Uh so one of course uh is
analog circuits. Um here we have an
example of like an RLC or RC uh kind of
uh an RC circuit. Um, and you could have
many little RC circuits like this that
are all coupled to each other. And in
general, you know, these can be noisy.
Uh, they could have, you know, more or
less noise or they could even have extra
noise sources included in them. Um, and
when we have a bunch of these coupled
together, what how they behave is
modeled by some kind of differential
equation or some stochastic differential
equation uh that describes how all the
voltages and currents change as a
function of time. Uh and so when we have
a system like that um well for one thing
it's not deterministic if there's you
know thermal noise uh for another um it
uh has information that flows in both
directions across all the couplings. Um
and it has components that are that
behave in a stateful way like these
capacitors their voltages are are
actually
playing kind of an algorithmically
important role of storing state. Um and
so you have kind of somehow you know
memory and processing happening in the
same place.
Um I think I wonder if there's any other
properties that that that vi well I
guess it was all four of them just with
that you know simple example of the um
you know stochcastic analog you know
coupled RC uh network um and and now
there's other kinds of circuits that are
uh you know use um that do processing
using uh kind of similar like networks
like like resistive crossbar arrays are
you know can be used for matrix vector
multiplication using uh you know an
array of uh of resistors. Now I'm not
sure if I would exactly consider this
like analog computing although maybe it
is in some way in that you're you're
doing addition using Kirchoff's you know
current law instead of using addition in
binary uh using um a bunch of uh you
know a bunch of logic gates and so we're
somehow using kind of the analog uh
current signals in order to do the
addition of uh you know of our numbers.
Um
and so I guess well another example of
of circuits that violate determinism
would be like uh stochastic magnetic
tunnel junctions where you can have um
stochastic switching which happens when
the magnetization direction in one of
the ferroagnetic layers uh can
spontaneously
switch uh the magnetization can switch
direction as a result of thermal
fluctuations. Um, and so now we have
like non-determinism baked in at kind of
the the smallest level of of the
circuit. Instead of building our
circuits out of um building blocks that
are deterministic, we're building it out
of building blocks that behave in a
stochastic way. Uh, and that can be used
for like stochastic computing for
example or it can be used for like for
computing based on like p bits or
probabistic bits. uh people commonly
like use things like this for um like uh
bolson machines uh would be one example
um and then I guess uh other kinds of
like non-deterministic behavior in in
circuits would be like uh stochastic
digital circuits which can still be
built without using any like more exotic
components like MTJs but just with
standard uh you know cos transistors. Um
but uh in in this kind of paradigm of
computing uh stochastic digital
circuits, we encode numbers in uh random
bits uh bits that are berni random
variables like like coin flips. Um and
the probability that the bit is one is
kind of encoding a number and so
different numbers are encoded by random
bits with different probabilities. Um
and so you can imagine that using this
way of like of formatting or encoding
numbers is more robust to errors than um
it is if if we just formatted all our
numbers in binary. Uh in if I have a a
binary number if I accidentally flipped
uh you know the least significant bit
that causes a pretty small error but if
I accidentally flipped uh the most
significant bit bit that creates
potentially like a catastrophic error.
And so that's kind of the reason that
standard like binary encoding is not the
most resilient to error uh to to like
bit flip errors. And so when we use
instead uh stochastic digital circuits
uh because our processing is resilient
to bit flip errors, we can in some sense
like cut corners with the design and not
build in as many guard rails that uh
prevent bit flip errors. uh and one
example of that would be um well I
mentioned earlier how synchroniz like
global centralized synch synchronization
is often assumed integrated circuits but
if you have some resilience against
bitflip errors you can often uh use some
kind of trick so that you don't have to
have a global uh clock that everything
is synchronized to or instead you could
have you know many local clocks and and
each you know different parts of the
chip are just kind of locally
synchronized uh but not perfectly those
local clocks can drift or skew a little
bit relative to each other which is
called polyynchronous clocking. Um and
and using methods like that that take
advantage of the error resilience of
this paradigm uh can allow you to uh you
know drive your circuit faster or to uh
use less energy basically. Um and then
of course there's approach there's other
kind of physics based approaches that uh
like optical optical computing or you
know integrated photonics for example um
which I won't get into uh very much um
but uh yeah some of our co-authors uh in
particular you know like Peter McMahon
is more of an expert on on that kind of
stuff but um I guess in general just
wanted to emphasize that there are a lot
of different kind of building blocks
that you could use to build circuits uh
you know make chips that um start to do
away some of these assumptions.
Um, oh, I guess another good example of
of a computing platform or you know
device that uh does away with one of
those assumptions would be memorrists
which are of course intended to behave
statefully. So the the way a memorister
behaves should depend on kind of its
history of what voltages have been
applied to it before. Uh so it kind of
gets rid of this assumption of
statelessness. Uh and then you can also
make like an emulator of a a memory uh
using you know transistors and
capacitors and so on. Uh so you can you
can even without having you know a
memory device per se you can still build
circuits that kind of behave in the same
way of of behaving statefully. Um
so I've talked about kind of a few
different you know platforms and
building blocks that can be used um to
make like physics based AS6. Uh and so
now uh you may be starting to wonder
well how do we know that uh these
devices are actually going to be useful
or like what kind of problems will we be
able to solve you know even if we build
a chip that is you know is isn't doesn't
have statelessness or determinism or
unidirectional information flow and so
on uh what's it going to be good for um
so this is where we need to think about
that um like hardware algorithm
codeesign approach I was talking about
uh so we we have some device which has
some you know physical processes that
occur on it. Uh and we think of that as
kind of this circle over here in this
vin diagram. Um and as we put it here as
like what physics wants to compute. Uh
because when you have like some um for
example some network of electrical
devices like you know transistors and
capacitors and so on uh there's going to
be some you know some mathematical
function that relates its inputs to its
outputs you know potentially some
complicated function uh which includes a
lot of you know physics that happens uh
but we don't know that that's useful per
se. So that's kind of what the physics
wants to compute. And there's also like
what uh functions are useful in our
algorithms. What you know what are kind
of the primitive building blocks of our
algorithms. Um and so what we want to do
is we want to find like the overlap of
these two sets basically and find the
operations that are performed
efficiently on a device due to the
physics of how the device works and are
also useful in uh you know in some
algorithm. basically. Um, so that's kind
of the idea of hardware algorithm code
design. Um, and so then I guess I'll
I'll talk a little bit about like
examples of how that might work. Um, so
I think like one good example of a class
of algorithms where we would expect
these like physics- based AS6 to perform
well is in uh well in machine learning
in general where you have a function
that is parameterized by a set of like
learned weights. Um because uh one thing
that's useful about this is that a you
know a neural network is adaptable in
some way and that if you make some
change to its activation function for
example and then retrain it uh it will
you know often or in general be able to
modify the weights so that it still
computes the the correct function uh but
just does it in a slightly different way
because now it it you've changed the
activation functions and also changed
the weights to somehow compensate for
So um similarly when if we have some
physics base ASIC that has uh some kind
of intricate physical processes that are
used to evaluate functions uh we don't
necessarily get to choose what those
functions are. um they might be you know
very complicated functions uh and
they're not necessarily you know
immediately useful but if we use if we
um combine those functions that are
natural to perform on the hardware with
a learning algorithm and trainable
weights then in some sense we expect the
uh the model to be able to adapt to the
um the functions that it is given
basically. Okay, so you can kind of
think of that as analogous to the idea
of training a model for some you know
different for for different kinds of
activation functions and you could also
train a model for uh that that can take
advantage of the physics on a you know
of the operations that are naturally
performed on some physics based ASIC. Um
so that's kind of one general class is
like training uh or and running you know
training an inference for neural
networks on physics based AS6. Um and in
fact a lot of the uh you know hardware
paradigms that uh we've talked about are
being used or are have been proposed to
be used for exactly that. Uh so we have
this area of like training and inference
for neural networks. Um another good
example is uh like scientific computing.
So a lot of the time you know some of
the most demanding um computations that
are done are simulating actual physical
systems. So as one example you could
think of like molecular dynamics uh
where you have some large uh molecule
which is basically a network of atoms
that are you know connected to each
other you know of course by you know
bonds and so on. Um and then there are
the laws of motion that govern you know
how all those atoms move, right? And in
general like you know the way that
people report kind of performance for
molecular dynamic simulation I believe
is is often quoted in like nanoseconds
per day. Like how long do you have to
run your uh or like how many days do you
have to run your simulation to simulate
a molecule evolving for like a nancond
is a relevant question in molecular
dynamics. And so that kind of goes to
show that somehow the physical system
itself, the molecule is much more
efficient at at running its own dynamics
than the uh you know than a digital
computer is. And so then we could ask
well is there some circuit that behaves
more like the actual molecule physically
or that has like similar equations of
motion to a molecule? Uh that would be a
lucky coincidence, right? If we could
find a circuit that has very similar
equations of motion to some molecule and
could use it to simulate the molecular
dynamics or you know more generally um
we can look at some of the properties of
the physical system in you know that's
that's there in molecular dynamics and
say well can we um do we really need all
these properties in our circuit that we
talked about before like you know
statelessness and unidirectionality etc
uh in order to build some you build some
algorithm for simulating the molecule.
Uh, and that's kind of a more general
approach of like we're not necessarily
looking for an exact mapping between the
dynamics of the circuit and the dynamics
of the molecule, but we're kind of
looking at a more abstract level like
what are the properties of the physical
system we're trying to simulate, what
are the properties of the circuit and is
there some uh kind of um agreement
between those in some way. Uh, so as a
good example would be determinism. uh in
molecular dynamic simulations of course
there's there's generally noise that's
added uh which represents the influence
of the heat bath. Uh you you oft you'll
simulate a molecule not just in a vacuum
but typically in some you know solvent
and that solvent could be simulated in
different ways uh either you know by
explicitly simulating a bunch of water
molecules or by adding kind of noise
terms in to uh simulate the effects of
random impacts from water molecules or
etc. Uh and because we're running an
algorithm where in some way there's like
random behavior uh which again modeling
the heat bath uh we could we start to
wonder if if we need to make if if it's
actually necessary for our circuit to
behave in a totally deterministic way or
if it's okay if our circuit has uh
random errors at some rate. Uh so I
think that's a good example of kind of
connecting the properties of the circuit
we're using for the comput for the
computing to the application that's
required by some like scientific
computing task. Um and and there may be
uh you know other ways to do this as
well. You know, for example, if I have a
molecule, the there um there isn't
necessarily like uh kind of something
that behaves like a global clock that's,
you know, talking to every single atom
and synchronizing their motions, right?
Only, you know, there's only kind of
local uh interaction and local
connectivity in in typically in
molecules. And so there might be a way
of using a um a computing architecture
that doesn't have a global clock or has
something more like that polyynchronous
clocking I was talking about uh and maps
onto the molecular dynamics problem
somehow and and similar kind of
arguments could apply for these these
other properties as well even if the
details of how that would work isn't uh
exactly worked out. Um, and so in
general, uh, you know, as as we were
talking about earlier, when we kind of
get rid of those idealized properties,
we are allowing our circuit to behave
more like a generic physical system that
we might find in nature. And so it might
end up that it's well suited to
simulating physical systems that occur
in nature like like molecules for
example. Um so another kind of class of
algorithms where we expect like physics-
based A6 to be useful is um well for one
thing in randomized algorithms in
general uh because we I was talking
about how um well if we don't require
our circuit to be deterministic we can
cut some corners and make it more energy
efficient and and fast. And so in a lot
of algorithms that actually require
randomness like uh MCMC for example or
or uh like sampling and you know basian
inference um there you know the
algorithm is naturally resilient to
errors because uh randomness is required
by the algorithm and so we expect you
know physics based as that get rid of
properties like determinism to be uh
well suited to these kind of algorithms
uh and and by a similar a very similar
argument in a lot of you know generative
AI like uh you know image generation,
video generation, materials discovery
which is you know for an example like
generating new molecules. Uh often these
are solved using like diffusion models
which are also like randomized
algorithms because they're basically
simulations of a stocastic differential
equation. uh which is actually similar
to the you know molecular dynamics that
the way that we model a molecule
evolving under a heat path is like a
differential equation that that is uh
based on all the forces uh between atoms
and Newton's laws and then we add noise
uh and similarly with a diffusion model
the way that we sample an image is by
running a stochcastic differential
equation you know which is has some
drift velocity and then some noise term
uh so in some sense there there's even a
similarity between you you know,
diffusion models and and molecular
dynamics at at some like algorithmic
level. Uh, and and that's actually one
of the applications we're uh very
interested in, I would say, is is
diffusion models in particular because
that's uh rapidly growing in kind of its
usefulness uh and its like computational
cost. Um and then there's also some work
uh on well you know we we had an earlier
paper thermodynamic linear algebra where
we talked about how you could use a a
kind of thermodynamic uh processor to
solve problems in linear algebra like
linear systems of equations or inverting
matrices matrix exponentials um and if
you're interested in that you can check
out the paper uh thermodynamic linear
algebra and then um there's yeah our
other paper that I actually talked about
last time I was on this uh um was the
thermodynamic Beijian inference where we
talk about how to use a thermodynamic
processing device for uh like sampling
from Beijian posteriors. Uh so those
were some examples of like different
applications area different application
areas and I tried to give a little bit
of intuition for like why we think
different application areas might map
well to like physics-based A6 and more
kind of I guess even more broadly like
why we expect that general purpose
digital architectures are kind of
overbuilt uh for a lot of these
applications or at least they are built
to at great expense to guarantee certain
properties which aren't not needed for
for many of these applications. Um so I
think that's you know basically what I
wanted to say about um kind of what
physics based basics are and uh you know
how we're thinking about algorithm
codees and what what we think they're
going to be useful for. I guess we also
talked a little bit about in this paper
about uh kind of where we see the field
going and what are some of the next
steps I guess and this calls to action.
So I I'll say a few words about that. Um
so for one thing uh there there are
going to be uh you know algorithms that
the GPU is very good at um and are
probably not going to benefit from are
not or at least not going to benefit as
much from you know very new
unconventional computing paradigms. Uh
but there's also going to be some
applications where that are not you know
very naturally suited to GPUs. Uh and so
that's one of the most or yeah one of
the first and fundamental things uh to
do in our calls to action is to kind of
identify the set of applications that
don't map well to GPUs or that GPUs
aren't well optimized for um and kind of
identify you know why they are not well
optimized why the GPU isn't well
optimized for those applications um and
have you know have a good understanding
of that uh so so that's one kind of call
to action and then another one uh of
course is actually co-designing the
algorithms and hardware uh for physics
based AS6. Uh so as and we give the
example here of how like transformers
have been designed you know to run well
on GPUs. Um and so similarly like what
what's kind of the equivalent of the
transformer for um uh for physics based
AS6 well you know maybe we don't know
yet. Uh maybe it's these uh energy based
transformers we're looking at. Well,
either way, I think there's a lot of
room to um you know, explore new
algorithms in hardware uh that will you
know have a good agreement between the
algorithm and physics based A6 uh and
can be used for you know AI. Um and then
uh well there's going to be yeah so we
talked about like developing the full
stack for physics based A6. So there's
basically just a lot of new kinds of
layers of software that are going to be
needed uh like simulation uh of so yeah
like first like how can we can we use
like a GPU to simulate how our physics
based ASIC would perform uh so that we
can kind of solve design problems before
we actually build it. uh and can we take
you know existing machine learning
algorithms and compile them so that
they'll run efficiently using our
physical primitives on the physics based
ASIC that's another thing like kind of a
compilation layer and so that will be
you know a significant amount of work um
and then I think we also have a note
about like yeah explaining goals uh you
know in a way explaining the field
basically in a way that's easy to
understand for people in different uh
from different backgrounds like
electrical engineering or computer
science and so on uh just because this
is a very like interdisciplinary field
at the moment. Um, which is one of the
things that's so uh exciting and fun
about it I think is that it it's very
truly like interdisciplinary and
combining physics and you know uh
engineering uh circuit design and
theoretical computer science in a very
and math and kind of very interesting
combination. Um so yeah, I think that
that covers everything I wanted to say
about the paper and um I guess at at
this point I'll take any any questions
if there were any other questions. Yeah.
Awesome.
Awesome. All right. Okay.
Here's where that took me. The the three
uncertainties.
What is a unifying framework for
cognitive science? What is a unifying
framework for computer science? And how
are those questions related especially
in the context of cognition as
inference/computee
as cognition?
like what are those sort of domain or
discipline scale synthesis in the
cognitive science and the computer
science department so to speak and what
does that look like as we increasingly
see those two used by and forward with
each other. So if you have any thoughts
go forward but that was just my where it
took me.
>> Interesting. Okay. Okay. So, right.
Okay. So, you're asking like what is a
unifying framework for cognitive science
or and or Yeah. And I guess a unifying
framework for computer science and are
you also kind of like like uh like
gesturing at like a unifying framework
that would unify both of those unifying
frameworks as well kind of or
>> Yeah. It's like all these branches
coming together that you brought
together with the authorship and and the
perspectives in this paper. And then
over here in cognitive sciences and
active inference, that's the quest of
the unifying cognitive model that
attention, memory, anticipation, all
these different cognitive phenomena
would be approached in a unifying
handling. And we're using those
probabilistic compute tools along the
way and even interpreting what the
materials
classical computers and unconventional
computers what they do as this kind of
like material intelligence.
So it is getting very hot and heavy in
that area. Um
>> I see.
>> Yeah. I see. Yeah. No, I definitely like
Yeah. Thinking about things like that as
well. I would say that I I haven't
explored as much like the uh kind of
interactions with the cognitive side uh
you know cognitive science side of
things although although I know there's
a lot of kind of rich interesting things
to think about there uh as like you know
for example like some some of uh you
know things in this paradigm people do
are things like spiking neural networks
and things like that that are at least
inspired by and arguably you know
behaving in a similar way perhaps to
thing you know things in the brain. Um
and and that was also something we
thought about a little bit in our in our
you know thermo basian inference paper
was uh can this can this somehow be
mapped onto ideas about like how you
know people reason uh under or you know
how yeah we yeah how people reason under
uncertainty things like that um so and
yeah I think there probably is a lot to
explore there also just goes to show
just how kind of like interdisiplinary
this field is um another thing I think
about in terms of like unification which
is is a a little bit uh different from
that but may you know have some overlaps
is like uni is like um kind of unifying
computer science or at least uh
computational complexity theory with uh
thermodynamics in some way which I think
is a kind of interesting idea. I'm not
sure like how realistic it is at this
point but um there are uh basically the
reason I think that there is is going to
be some overlap there and perhaps like
some unification is that these are like
kind of some of the two two important
theories that give us estimates of how
much uh you know basically how much work
it takes to do something. Uh so
computational complexity theory gives us
estimates of you know how does the
amount of time uh or you could also
think of it as like or well the amount
of space or even the amount of energy
required scale with uh the size of your
computation that you have to do
basically. And similarly in
thermodynamics you can derive results
that tell you how much like physical
work you have to do uh in meaning like
literally the amount of energy uh that
you you spend or dissipate in order to
uh perform some uh you know perform some
change in the system state and there
already are some small like overlaps
where this becomes more explicit like of
course landower's principle and and
similar like generalizations of
landour's principle that uh make a link
between thermodynamic work and
computational operations. But in
general, I think that there's a larger
kind of like program that could be
pursued of um mapping statements in
computational complexity theory somehow
into thermodynamic statements about how
much work is required to bring about
some change in state of of a system
basically. Uh so I think that's kind of
another and and that could even perhaps
overlap with like the idea you were
mentioning of like unifying uh kind of
these not you know exotic computing
architectures with with co cognitive
science and stuff like that. So yeah I
think that's kind kind of an exciting
idea.
>> Cool. I'll ask one more question then
read the questions that people have
added in the chat. So, how do you see
biology and biological materials in the
scheme? Figure three seems to be mainly
abiotic
focused.
>> Uh, figure three. Um, sorry, what was
the the last phrase you said? It was it
was something focused.
>> Abiotic.
>> Abiotic. What does that Sorry, what does
that mean?
>> These uh are not arising from a living
system. they're machined or engineered
though there's some analogy with
biological systems but just how did that
come up or where do you see biological
processes and materials generation in
this scheme that the paper lays out?
>> I see. Okay. Yeah. Okay. So, I'm going
to kind of I'm going to venture a little
bit outside of my uh kind of wheelhouse
here because I I'm not uh you know an
expert in in biology by any means. Um
and so that's why I'm a little bit more
comfortable kind of drawing analogies
between the behaviors of these circuits
and like generic dynamical systems like
a molecule for example. Uh but of course
uh you know organisms are also made out
of molecules. Um and even at a higher
level of you know even at a higher
structural level organisms might have
some similarities uh you know in in
terms of those properties I was
mentioning before. I guess um
in general yeah I guess yeah one example
might be good was that Kuramoto model
thing I was just talking about. Uh so
there I've seen that there's some work
on using the Kuramoto model which the
model of how a bunch of different
oscillators can synchronize with each
other to model how um synchronization uh
can occur in the brain. Uh which I think
has to do with uh you know brain waves
that are that are you know happening
with different frequencies although I
don't know much about that. Um but I I
think that general the and I'm not sure
if people know whether the kuramoto
model is actually a good uh or whether
it's a welljustified model of that but
at any rate the kuromoto model is a
decentralized model of synchronization
where you have a bunch of things that
have you know have pair-wise
interactions talking to each other
instead of one global clock that's
coordinating everything. And so there we
see uh a physics-based ASIC that kind of
gets gets rid of assumption 4 might be
more similar in architecture to a
biological system than it is to
something like a GPU. Um, so I think
that that's like one way of answering
your question is that I I would expect
that physics-based AS6 may have more
similarities in architecture to
biological systems being uh, you know,
decentralized and uh, although I don't I
don't really know enough about you know
kind of typical like biological systems
to probably give a very good answer but
uh, yeah, I think that's one thought I
have on it.
>> Cool. Okay, from the live chat, Gortto68
wrote, "Cubism is my jam." That was just
a comment. And then a question, Max,
have you noticed a trend in the last 8
years in a new physics of geometry and
ultra high frequency applications to
metamaterials and nanom machines?
>> Um, let's see. Okay. Trent in the last
eight years of um metamaterials and
nanom machine. Oh, wait. What was the
first part? something relating to
nanomaterials and metamaterial
>> new physics of geometry and ultra high
frequency applications to metamaterials
and nanom machines
>> materials and nanom machines um I I
would say I have not noticed that but I
haven't been very focused on those
fields uh so yeah I I haven't noticed it
but that doesn't mean it isn't happening
uh but yeah it sound sounds interesting
yeah
>> what has changed over the last eight
years or months or days Why is this
coming to fruition in your research and
development at this time?
>> That's a good question. So, one thing
that's changed, I guess, in yeah, let's
say the last decade or something is that
uh quantum computing turned out to be
like harder than a lot of people thought
it was going to be, I think. Um and uh
so I I I remember like early on when I
was beginning grad school uh there were
a lot of people uh who were and I was
well not quite well I was kind of I I
was kind of working more on the theory I
guess of like the thermodynamics of
quantum computers but there were a lot
of people at that time who were working
on like quantum compilers uh things like
that that were supposed to make the they
were supposed to solve the problems of
like software engineering for a quantum
computer. And that just kind of goes to
show how optimistic people were at that
point, I think, because people already
kind of treated the engineering
challenge of building a quantum computer
as like a foregone conclusion that would
happen in, you know, the next decade or
something and then we would run into
this problem of needing to be able to
design scalable software for it. But as
you know, as far as I know, it it didn't
quite turn out that way. And the problem
is still uh we're still stuck with the
problem of actually building, you know,
the large uh quantum computers. And so
now people are thinking more about like
error correction codes and things like
that that uh that you know will
basically allow us to to scale them more
easily. But I guess that that's one
reason why at least in in the story of
how I became interested in these kind of
approaches to computing that these are
unconventional classical approaches to
computing that you know don't have the
well they they still you know have some
scalability and engineering challenges
associated with them. They're not the
same kinds of challenges that uh were so
hard and still are so hard in quantum
computing. I guess uh that would be one
answer. And the other answer I guess is
hap uh is kind of related to what I was
talking about with the end of dinard
scaling although that happened you know
more like two decades ago um but
arguably it's now is when it start it's
kind of being acutely most acutely felt
I guess uh the end of dinard scaling
because we're finally getting to the
point where um the energy costs are just
kind of accelerating massively uh due to
our you know rapidly expanding compute
needed for AI. So those are kind of the
two things I would point to, I guess.
>> Cool. Yeah. Where did the paper take you
all and the authors? Like
where do you where do you go from here?
What what milestones are you looking for
next?
>> Right. Well, yeah. So, so at Normal
Computing, uh, you know, we're making
our own chips. Um and so we have you
know milestones for those for the
development of those chips uh which have
to do with like specific AI generative
AI algorithms that we want to run on
them. So that involves like simulating
how the chips are going to perform and
and getting out kind of estimates of
their performance from our simulations.
Uh building the chips and we've already
made uh a lot of progress on on that. Um
and uh and then kind of thinking through
like how these chips are actually going
to be used like commercially. Uh so
that's when I when I think about kind of
like my piece of this puzzle of um
physics based AS6. It really has to do
with our uh stochastic digital kind of
the thermodynamic stoastic digital
processors we're making at uh at normal
computing to solve some of these
problems in AI.
Very cool. Uh I guess one sort of last
question and then feel free to make any
comments like what is the educational
trajectory?
How do people learn up on this? Is it
going to look like type theory and
programming languages and computer
science undergrad or what kinds of
background are useful to be learning and
getting familiar with to kind of skate
to where the puck is going?
>> Mhm. Right. So I would say that for one
thing u you know definitely uh people
experienced in you know silicon
engineering uh you know if if people who
have a skill set in designing
conventional AS6 and have a a deep
knowledge of you know of of integrated
circuits from that well you know that
knowledge will absolutely I think
transfer over to um kind of more
unconventional architectures and it
might be even more uh might be even more
unthink about because you it's kind of
throwing away some of the rules that are
uh it's kind of like you solving some of
the same kinds of problems but where
many of the rules have been thrown away
I guess so it becomes kind of a
different game. Uh so that's one
background one way of getting there. Uh
another which is more which is the way
that I kind of got here is the uh kind
of more theoretical physics and in
particular like statistical physics in
thermodynamics end up being very
relevant uh especially because a lot of
algorithms in AI have some algorithms in
AI have been designed inspired by or
based on uh uh ideas in statistical
physics. So like for example diffusion
models um or more generally in like
machine learning there's like beian
inference models and and Monte Carlo
methods that are like deep deeply
related to uh things in in statistical
physics. Uh and so in general like
having both knowledge of the algorithms
and of the physical pictures that those
algorithms map onto kind of puts you in
I think a good position to think about
like what might the ideal piece of
hardware look like to run this
algorithm. Uh because you can kind of
think about like what physical models
map on to an algorithm I guess. So
that's another background that that I
think is a good kind of route to this uh
this way of thinking is like statistical
physics. uh etc. Um and then of course
uh people with like yeah people with
math math backgrounds uh you know math
statistics uh computer science um and AI
in general are of course all important
and especially uh when we get into
things like um performance bottlenecks
like uh knowing you know knowing the
answers to the questions like what's the
most costly part of running this uh
pipeline if I'm running a fusion model
or I'm running a large language model
where is the majority of the computation
being done? Uh which is kind of related
to like theoretical computer science and
complexity theory but isn't quite the
same is it's more of like a practical
question of like where are the actual
bottlenecks in practice. Um so and so
you know that would be the skill set
more of people who do like you know
large scale machine learning
infrastructure training and inference
and stuff like that. Um so I think all
those like skill sets are you know
people uh are in a very good position to
kind of move into this field and I do
hope that more and more people do start
to get involved in this. Yeah.
>> Cool. I'm going to read a very
interesting related comment but then
feel free to make any last
additions there. Okay. Tal Zahed wrote,
"How digital education will advance with
AI systems running on special chips A6
using probabilistic models to
personalize learning over time. As
digital education platforms scale
globally, delivering personalized and
adaptive learning which requires low
latency AI computation. This research
explores the deployment of stochastic AI
models on AS6 to achieve real-time
adaptation and user learning paths,
reducing energy consumption while
maximizing student outcomes.
>> I see that that does sound like really
interesting research. And what I like
about it is it it's like it's an example
of like kind of connecting the full
stack end to end in the sense that like
it it talks about the the end
application. what are some properties of
that application like requiring low
latency and adaptive behavior although
I'm not I you know I haven't read up
very much on the application but it's it
sounds plausible that those are
requirements and and then connecting
that to like what algorithms we're going
to use for it and and in particular like
you know large language models or or
beijian uh reasoning models and then
like what hardware would be required to
accelerate those algorithms. So kind of
connecting the all the way from the
application to the algorithms to the
hardware is exactly the right way of
thinking in order to to do something
meaningful I think. So I really like
that uh comment. Yeah.
>> Cool. And yes closing the loop with the
improvements and the improving
improvement.
>> Any other comments?
>> Um no I think yeah I think I covered
everything. Uh and yeah just again I
really enjoyed coming on. Uh so yeah
always always a pleasure. Uh and yeah
thanks for having me on.
>> Cool. Looking forward to the next
episode.
>> All right,
>> see you.
>> Sounds good. Thanks. See you later.
>> Bye.